My name is Punmaram and hers is Raeta.
Wherever I go, she goes.
I look after a herd of 250 camels.
They've always belonged to my family.
My two brothers are coming tomorrow.
Every year we go to the great
meeting of camel raisers.
It's a long trip on the other side
of the desert South of Rajasthan.
My oldest brother lives in the village.
His name is Sutaram.
He wears the white turban of wisdom.
During the year,
he works the wool of our camels.
Our tethers, our blankets,
and our rugs are woven from camel hair.
At the great meeting,
he's the one who speaks for the family.
Sunaram is my little brother.
He wears the yellow turban of business.
He's always traveling,
looking for new studs.
He's the family business man.
At the great meeting,
he's the one who sells the camels.
As for me,
I've taken the camel-colored turban
because I'm always with them.
I guide them from pasture to pasture.
I saw them all being born.
They've always seen me here.
My brothers say that
I'm the father of camels.
[Foreign spoken audio]
When they're born,
the camels aren't strong enough
to reach their mother's udders.
That's why I'm here,
so that my camels
grow strong and live a long time.
I belong to the great Rabari tribe.
In Persian, rabar means guide,
but we are not guides for men,
we are guides for the camels.
I was 12-years-old when I left my village
to lead this herd with my father.
Today, it's the biggest one
in Rajasthan with the best camels.
My brothers and I are known for that.
Every year, to prove that our camels
are the strongest and the fastest,
one of the three of us goes to the meeting
by crossing the great desert alone.
He rides his favorite camel.
However, for years now,
I've been the one
to cross the desert with Raeta.
[Foreign spoken audio]
My brothers are leaving
tomorrow for the great meeting.
They'll take the road
that goes round the desert.
I'll go across it, right across
the sand where there is no road.
While I'm away, my herd stays here.
It won't move because of the newborn.
I've had 60 this year
and there are more to come.
This one's for pretty soon,
but I know she'll wait for me to get back.
They always wait for me to get back.
There's nothing but females
in my herd and a single male.
I can't keep the young males.
As soon as there are two,
they start to fight.
I've got 40 this year,
they'll be going with my brothers.
[Foreign spoken audio]
We'll be at the meeting at the full moon.
This year,
my brothers don't want me to do it.
They say I'm too old to cross the sand.
However, I'm going to go anyway.
Raeta is my best camel.
She will guide me.
[Foreign spoken audio]
Jaisalmer, the gateway to the desert.
Beyond its walls, the tale begins.
The land of sand.
No more water.
The man who doesn't forget
lives in the citadel.
All the camel herders
come to listen to him.
He tells the story of our tribe.
In the beginning,
the God Shiva created the first camel,
and then he created
the first man of my tribe
to take care of this camel.
The first camel had five legs.
Seeing that, the first man asked,
how the camel
could walk with a leg under its belly.
Shiva took the fifth leg in his hand
and shoved it into the air.
[Foreign spoken audio]
That's why the camel has a hump.
He said that we were there
to take care of this camel.
[Foreign spoken audio]
In the desert,
there are no differences between men.
In the desert, it's the camel
that makes the difference.
Raeta will carry me
across the dunes for seven days.
If our way is straight,
we'll find the city of the Desert Queen.
Behind her, the great meeting.
My brothers also have a long road,
and the young camels
they've taken with them are still wild.
They've never been tied up.
They've never left their mothers.
[Foreign spoken audio]
Here, everything moves.
From one day to the next, you no
longer recognize the face of the desert.
That's how the Rabari
became nomads, by following the winds,
the dunes, the rains
and the grazing land to feed their camels.
My brothers will be worried
if they get there before I do.
They'll blame themselves
for having let me leave.
Out there where so many men
have lost their way.
However, Reita is strong.
She can go five days without water,
if the wind stops blowing.
[Foreign spoken audio]
The great beauty.
All tribes gather
at the first moon in April.
The leaders gather,
listen to complaints, mete out justice
and divide up their territories.
The families marry off children
and their best animals too.
The stories that are told here,
quickly become legends.
Tribes have been coming here
for centuries.
It's the only place
that has enough water for 100,000 animals.
A great river runs under the sand.
It has never dried up.
[Foreign spoken audio]
There are caravaners, shepherds,
merchants, every race of cattle,
and all the families
that live from cattle raising.
Each tribe has its own reputation.
Anything to do with the camels,
it's our family that people come to see.
It's my elder brother
who does the talking.
However, he won't say anything.
Not until the three of us
are there together again
and everybody knows that.
[Foreign spoken audio]
My brothers are ripe, I'm getting old.
The day a camel gives birth,
she only has eyes for her baby.
She can't lead a herd anymore.
She loses her flexibility
and her faithfulness.
That's why Raeta hasn't had any children.
I've needed her too much.
[Foreign spoken audio]
She'll have one next year
and she'll bring it up.
This is our last trip.
I was a child when my father
took me off to live with his herd.
At first, I was lost in the middle
of all those camels.
I had to get used to drinking
murky water and sleeping out in the cold.
Then my father taught me
to recognize and count them
at a single glance
and how to talk to them from the throat.
One day he said to me,
man lives on the ground.
When he climbs onto a camel, he takes off.
The city of the Desert Queen.
The trail ends here.
It is said that the plague
grew in these walls.
The citizens blamed the rats.
Then a woman came.
She gathered the dead children
and changed them into rats
in order to bring them back to life.
She said they would be her children
and that all life must be respected,
even a rat's life.
The epidemic ended and to thank her,
the people built her a temple
For our family,
she became the goddess of the desert,
the goddess that protects
children from disease.
She said that all men
and animals are her children.
She watches over my camels.
[Foreign spoken audio]
Men think that
the solitude of the desert is terrible.
For me, solitude is here.
I have no life without my herd.
They're all here.
My brothers say
I should go back to the village.
That I will have to stop
following the camels one day.
As long as I'm strong enough
to help a camel be born,
I'll stay where I am.